Richard Rodgers Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Richard Rodgers Collection1917-1980 (bulk 1925-1979)
ML30.58
Rodgers, Richard, 1902-1979
circa 2,700 items 45 boxes 20 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The collection consists predominantly of Rodgers's music holographs--sketches, vocal scores (many with lyric sheets included) and short scores. In addition, the collection includes full scores for 8 of the Rodgers and Hammerstein shows. Also included is a small number of programs, photographs, miscellaneous papers, and a few miscellaneous items.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Hammerstein, Oscar, 1895-1960.; Hart, Lorenz, 1895-1943.; Rodgers, Richard, 1902-1979.; Rodgers, Richard, 1902-1979.
Subjects
Musical sketches.; Musicals--Scores.; Musicals--Vocal scores with piano.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Richard Rodgers; 1956-1979.
Gift; Dorothy Rodgers; 1979?-1995.
Gift; Rogers & Hammerstein Organization; to 1995.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Correspondence: Richard Rodgers Papers, 1914-1989, Billy Rose Theatre Collection at the New York Public Library for the Performing Arts at Lincoln Center, 40 Lincoln Center Plaza, New York, N.Y. 10023-7498 USA
Access and Restrictions
The Richard Rodgers Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Performing Arts Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use. Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1902, June 28 Richard Rodgers is born to Dr. William and Mamie (Levy) Rodgers in New York City
1917 Composes music for the amateur production One Minute Please
1919 Composes music for the amateur production Up Stage and Down
1919, Dec. 19 First collaborates with Lorenz Hart
1919-1921 Attends Columbia University
1920 Composes music for the amateur productions You'd Be Surprised and Fly With Me, and his first professional production Poor Little Ritz Girl
1921 Composes music for the amateur productions Say Mama, You'll Never Know and Say It With Jazz
1921-1923 Attends Institute of Musical Art Juilliard)
1922 Composes music for the amateur productions The Chinese Lantern and Jazz a la Carte
1923 Composes music for the amateur productions If I Were King and A Danish Yankee in King Tut's Court
1924 Composes music for the amateur production Temple Bells and The Prisoner of Zenda, and the professional production The Melody Man
1925 Composes music for his last amateur production Bad Habits of 1925, and professional productions The Garrick Gaieties and Dearest Enemy
1926 Composes music for the night club revue The Fifth Avenue Follies and the shows The Girl Friend, The Garrick Gaieties, Lido Lady London) Peggy-Ann and Betsy
1927 Composes music for the shows One Dam Thing After Another (London) and A Connecticut Yankee
1928 Composes music for the shows She's My Baby, Present Arms and Chee-Chee
1929 Composes music for the shows Spring Is Here and Heads Up! (London)
1930 Composes music for the shows Simple Simon and Evergreen (London)
1930, March 5 Marries Dorothy Feiner
1931, Jan. 11 Daughter, Mary Rodgers is born
1931 Composes music for the shows America's Sweetheart and The Hot Heiress (film)
1932 Composes music for the films Love Me Tonight and The Phantom President
1933 Composes music for the film Hallelujah, I'm a Bum
1934 Composes music for the film Hollywood Party
1935, March 5 Daughter, Linda Rodgers is born
1935 Composes music for the shows Mississippi (film) and Jumbo
1936 Composes music for the shows On Your Toes and Dancing Pirate (film)
1937 Composes music for the shows Babes in Arms and I'd Rather Be Right
1938 Composes music for the shows Fools For Scandal (film), I Married An Angel and The Boys From Syracuse
1939 Composes music for the shows Too Many Girls and Ghost Town (ballet)
1940 Composes music for the shows Higher and Higher and Pal Joey
1941 Composes music for the film They Met in Argentina
1942 Composes music for the show By Jupiter
1943 Composes additional music for a revival of A Connecticut Yankee, and composes music for his first show collaboration with Oscar Hammerstein II -- Oklahoma!
1945 Composes music for the shows Carousel and State Fair (film)
1947 Composes music for the show Allegro
1949 Composes music for the show South Pacific
1951 Composes music for the show The King And I
1952 Composes background score for the television documentary Victory at Sea
1953 Composes music for the show Me and Juliet
1955 Composes music for the show Pipe Dream
1957 Composes music for the television musical Cinderella (remade in 1965 with an additional song)
1958 Composes music for the show Flower Drum Song
1959 Composes music for the show The Sound of Music
1960 Composes background score for television documentary Winston Churchill--The Valiant Years
1962 Writes music and lyrics for the show No Strings, and additional songs for the remake of the film State Fair
1962-1969 Is President and Producing Director, Music Theater of Lincoln Center
1965 Composes music, with lyrics by Stephen Sondheim, for the show Do I Hear a Waltz?, and writes music and lyrics for additional songs added to the film version of The Sound of Music
1967 Writes music and lyrics for the television musical Androcles and The Lion
1970 Composes music, with lyrics by Martin Charnin, for the show Two by Two
1976 Composes music, with lyrics by Sheldon Harnick, for the show Rex
1979 Composes music, with lyrics by Martin Charnin and Raymond Jessel, for the show I Remember Mama
1979, Dec. 30 Richard Rodgers dies
Scope and Content Note
The Richard Rodgers Collection at the Library of Congress consists predominantly of Rodgers' music holographs -- sketches, piano-vocal scores (many with lyric sheets included) and short scores. In addition, the collection includes the full scores for eight of the Rodgers and Hammerstein shows (Allegro, Carousel, Flower Drum Song, The King and I, Oklahoma, Pipe Dream, The Sound of Music, and South Pacific). The majority of these scores are in the hand of the orchestrator Robert Russell Bennett, but other orchestrators are represented and identified in this guide whenever possible. The collection also includes a small number of programs, photographs, miscellaneous papers, and a few miscellaneous items. A few items have been transferred to the Motion Picture Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division -- Rodgers' "gold record" for The Sound of Music; two video cassettes of home movies; and one cassette tape recorded by Zoe Hyde-Thomson consisting of Rodgers' reminiscences during World War II. The two video cassettes of home movies are from the 20s & 30s, includes scenes w/ Larry Hart, Rodgers' family, and theatre & Hollywood people, such as Fannie Brice, Edna Ferber, Dorothy Fields, Herbert Fields, Lew Fields, Charlie Ruggles, Jean Harlow, Leila Hyams, Herbert Marshall, Al Jolson, Harry Langdon, and director Lewis Milestone on the set of "Hallelujah, I'm a Bum") 2c (1 including people above, w/ Mrs. Rodgers voiceover, the 2nd showing Mrs. Rodgers & her daughters, w/ no voice over), si. & sd., b/w, 3/4" Videocasettes VSA0082-83.
Series I -- Show Music -- has been divided into Rodgers' manuscripts and the full scores; each of these sections has been organized alphabetically by show title and by song title within each show. In the instances when a Broadway musical either was revised, subsequently filmed, or a film musical was re-made, the materials for subsequent productions have been interfiled with the materials for the earlier production. When there are collections of sketches for a show, they are at the end of the materials for that show. Where a collection of sketches contains material from more than one show, the sketches are listed with the show which appears most often; cross-references have been provided for other shows appearing within these sketches. Other collections of sketches, representing a variety of shows, are placed in the Miscellaneous Sketches series; they are listed in chronological order (as nearly as can be determined), and are designated M.S. 1 (i.e., Miscellaneous Sketches 1), etc. Known song titles from these sketches are also cross-referenced in the appropriate shows. When most sketches in a collection are identifiable, the occasional "unidentified" item is listed in the order in which it appears; when most of the sketches in a collection are unknown, there is only a general reference to the fact that unidentified sketches are included. When a portion of a song title is crossed through on the music, it is also crossed through in this guide. The appendix at the end of this guide is an alphabetical list of all of Rodgers' songs represented in this collection and where they can be found. This appendix does not include the full scores.
The music for I Picked a Daisy, Lawrence of Arabia and the second film of State Fair were found together in a way that necessitated our making a best guess as to which materials were intended for which show. Our determinations should be construed as educated speculation, not fact.
The full scores contain many examples of show material that was deleted or replaced with new orchestrations. In a few cases, well known selections are conspicuously absent, most notably, "Carousel Waltz" and "Soliloquy" from Carousel. The full scores are organized alphabetically by show, and by song titles within shows. Unfamiliar titles, and items such as "bridges," and "utilities" are grouped together in Miscellaneous sections at the end of each show. A number of the full scores are marked "N/G," apparently indicating that the score was "No Good" and was not used in the final incarnation of the show.
This collection is an exquisite representation of the working life of a composer in both the breadth and the depth of the material it encompasses: close to 1,000 known song titles (some in various stages of composition), over 80 shows, and hundreds of untitled sketches are represented, primarily as holographs. The assembled materials span approximately sixty-two years (1917-1979), encompassing both Rodgers' amateur and professional life. Rodgers later works are most completely represented, but almost all significant early works are represented as well. There are also a number of lyric sketches for those works on which Rodgers acted as his own lyricist.
Rodgers' melodic prodigiousness is evidenced in the collection by page after page of his sketches. They reveal intricacies of his working methods, for instance, there are lyric sheets with annotations by Rodgers indicating which syllables to accent, some have rhythms notated in the margins, or a melody may be scrawled on the back. There are series of sketches which show the evolution of a song -- giving three or four alternative themes, often with different time signatures and in different styles.
The Rodgers and Hammerstein Fact Book by Stanley Green and the Catalog of the American Musical by Tommy Krasker and Robert Kimball were enormously helpful in determining correct song titles, as well as identifying the shows for which the songs were written or in which they were sung. Scott Willis, a Rodgers and Hart specialist, was gracious with both his time and knowledge, identifying a number of untitled pieces from the collection. Enormous thanks are due to Albert Tucker for his yeoman like work on both the processing of the collection and the creation of this guide.
Mark Eden Horowitz, 1995
Organization of the Richard Rodgers Collection
The Richard Rodgers Collection is organized into five series:
Show Music
Non-show Music
Miscellaneous Sketches
Photographs
Miscellaneous
http://lccn.loc.gov/2003561025
Container List
- Show Music (Box 1-18, Box 22-45)
  Series I -- Show Music -- has been divided into Rodgers' manuscripts and the full scores; each of these sections has been organized alphabetically by show title and by song title within each show. In the instances when a Broadway musical either was revised, subsequently filmed, or a film musical was re-made, the materials for subsequent productions have been interfiled with the materials for the earlier production. When there are collections of sketches for a show, they are at the end of the materials for that show. Where a collection of sketches contains material from more than one show, the sketches are listed with the show which appears most often; cross-references have been provided for other shows appearing within these sketches. The full scores contain many examples of show material that was deleted or replaced with new orchestrations.
  Note: The show I Picked a Daisy (ca. 1960), lyrics by Alan Jay Lerner, was unproduced. The collaboration between Rodgers and Lerner was terminated, Lerner subsequently completed the show with Burton Lane and it became On a Clear Day You Can See Forever.
  The Show Music has been divided into Rodgers' manuscripts and the full scores; each of these sections has been organized alphabetically by show title and then by song title within each show.
  - Manuscripts (Box 1-18)
    - Allegro (1947) lyrics by Oscar Hammerstein II
      - Allegro, Holograph sketch in pencil; 3 p.; Includes: [3] p. of unidentified holograph sketches, one dated "July 1, '43" (Box-folder 1/1)
      - Allegro, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [8] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [2] p. (Box-folder 1/1)
      - But the days on a planet see: [Sketches for Allegro: no. 3]
      - Come home, Holograph sketch in pencil; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/2)
      - Come home, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; 5 p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/2)
      - A fellow needs a girl, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [3] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/3)
      - Finale act one, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; 13 p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [6] p.; Includes: "What a lovely day for the wedding!" "I have let the time run on" "It may be a good idea for Joe" "To have & to hold" "Wish them well" (Box-folder 1/4)
      - The gentleman is a dope, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [7] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/5)
      - Good idea for Joe see: [Sketches for Allegro: no. 3]
      - Grandma see: [Sketches for Allegro: no. 3]
      - I have let the time run on see: [Sketches for Allegro: no. 3]
      - I know it can happen again, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [2] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/6)
      - It's a darn nice campus, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [2] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Money isn't everything, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; 8 p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [3] p. (Box-folder 1/8)
      - One foot, other foot, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; 6 p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [3] p. (Box-folder 1/9)
      - Opening act I see: [Sketches for Allegro: no. 3]
      - Opening sequence, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; 6 p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [2] p. (Box-folder 1/10)
      - Poor Joe!, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [1] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/11)
      - Possibly I'm cynical see: [Sketches for Allegro: no. 3]
      - Sitting on the porch in the moonlight, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [2] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/12)
      - So far, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [4] p. (Box-folder 1/13)
      - To have and to hold see: [Sketches for Allegro: no. 3]
      - Two more [loves] see: [Sketches for Allegro: no. 1]
      - Two short years, Holograph sketch in pencil; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/14)
      - Two short years, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [2] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/14)
      - What a lovely day for a wedding see: [Sketches for Allegro: no. 3]
      - The Wildcats are on a rampage, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [3] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet [1] p.; Uniform title: Wildcats (Box-folder 1/15)
      - Will you marry me?, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [3] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/16)
      - Wish them well: finale act I, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [3] p. (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Yatata!, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; 9 p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [3] p.; Uniform title: Yatata, yatata, yatata (Box-folder 1/18)
      - You are never away, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; 6 p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/19)
      - You never had it so good, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [3] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/20)
      - [Sketches for Allegro: no. 1], Holograph sketches in pencil; [4] p.; Includes: Yatata, yatata, [yatata] Two more loves [The gentleman is a dope]: She doesn't belong to me (Box-folder 1/21)
      - [Sketches for Allegro: no. 2], Holograph sketches in pencil; [2] p.; Includes: Money isn't everything Poor Joe (Box-folder 1/21)
      - [Sketches for Allegro: no 3], Holograph sketches in pencil; 9 p. + [6] p. (variously paginated); Includes: p. 1-2: "Opening act I" p. 2: "Grandma," "One foot, other foot" p. 3: "One foot, other foot" p. 4: "A fellow needs a girl," "It's a darn nice campus" p. 5: "The Wildcats are on a rampage" p. 6: "So far," "You are never away" p. 7: "Sitting on the porch [in the moonlight]," "What a lovely day for the wedding" p. 8-9: "What a lovely day for the wedding"(cont.), "I have let the time run on," "Possibly I'm cynical" p. [10]: "[Unidentified]," "But the days on a planet," "Two short years" p. [11]: "Wish them well," "To have and to hold," p. [12]: "I have let the time run on," "Two more loves," "[Allegro]: The lady in bed" p. [13]: "What a lovely day for the wedding," "Good idea for Joe" p. [14]: "Verse [A] fellow needs [a girl]: Marjorie," "Sitting on the porch [in the moonlight]," "You are never away" p. [15]: "Grandma," "[Unidentified]," "Fellow needs [a girl]" (Box-folder 1/21)
    - The American Idea (1973) television score
      - The American idea: main title theme, Holograph condensed score in pencil; 2 p.; Note: dated Oct. 1972 (Box-folder 1/22)
      - [The American idea], Holograph condensed score in pencil; 14 p.; Note: first program of projected ABC-TV series, televised 3/18/73.; Includes: "Sequence I: New England" "Sequence II: the Tuttles" "Sequence III: Harvard University" "Sequence IV: Mr. Tuttle" "Sequence V: Valley Forge" "Sequence VI: Independance Hall" "Sequence VII: Salem/William Penn/the Amish/the Mormons" "Sequence VIII" "Sequence IX" "Sequence X" "Sequence XI" (Box-folder 1/22)
    - America's Sweetheart (1931) lyrics by Lorenz Hart
      - I want a man See also: [M.S. 1] in MISCELLANEOUS SKETCHES, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil, no lyric; [3] p.; Note: originally written for Winkle Town but used in America's Sweetheart (Box-folder 1/23)
      - There's so much more see: [Sketches for One Dam Thing After Another]
      - [Sketches for America's Sweetheart], Holograph sketches in pencil; [5] p.; Includes: p. [1]: "Ope[ning] act I" p. [2]: "My sweet!" p. [3]: "Innocent ch[orus] girls [of yesterday]," "Movies," "In Californ - I.A." p. [4]: "[I've got five dollars]: $5," "[Unidentified]" p. [5]: "[Unidentified]," "[A lady must live]: Ladies must live" (Box-folder 1/24)
    - Androcles and the Lion (1967) television musical, lyrics by Richard Rodgers
      - Don't be afraid of an animal, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [4] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheets (2); [1] p. (Box-folder 1/25)
      - The emperor's thumb, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [2] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/26)
      - Emperor's thumb (extension), Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [2] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheets (2); [1] p. (Box-folder 1/26)
      - Ferrovius, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [2] p.; Note: 3 measures at bottom of p. [2] notated "New ending."; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/27)
      - Follow in our footsteps, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [2] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/28)
      - No more waiting: verse., Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [1] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/29)
      - No more waiting, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [3] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/29)
      - Strangers, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [2] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/30)
      - Strangers reprise, Typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/30)
      - Strangers reprise, Typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/30)
      - Strength is my weakness See also: [Two by Two sketches], Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [3] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet; [1] p.; Typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 1/31)
      - Velvet paws, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [2] p. (Box-folder 1/32)
      - [Sketches for Androcles and the Lion], Holograph sketches in pencil; [4] p.; Includes: p. [1]: "Velvet paws," "Stranger[s]" p. [2]: "[Unidentified]," "[The] emperor's thumb," "[Unidentified]" p. [3]: "Don't be afraid [of an animal]" p. [4]: "[Unidentified]" (Box-folder 1/33)
      - [Lyrics sheets and lyric sketches for Androcles and the Lion], Holograph (pencil) and typed lyric sheets and lyric sketches; [22] p.; Includes: Don't be afraid of an animal The emperor's thumb Emperor's thumb extension Follow in our footsteps No more waiting No more waiting verse Strangers Strangers reprise [Strength is my weakness] [Velvet paws]: gentle paws [Unidentified] (Box-folder 1/34)
      - [Miscellaneous Androcles and the Lion], Contents: [Letter]: Typed letter from Duane Garrison, secretary to Mr. Rodgers; [1] p. Dated September 21, 1967 [Breakdown of scenes]: Typed list; [1] p. Musical number run down: Typed list; 2 p. [List of musical numbers]: Typed list; [1] p. [Script]: Typed script, annotations in red ink & pencil; p. 42-51 [Notes]: Holograph in pencil; [3] p. (Box-folder 1/35)
    - Babes in Arms (1937) lyrics by Lorenz Hart
      - All at once, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [4] p.; Laid in: carbon copy of typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 2/1)
      - Patter for All at once, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; 2 p.; Laid in: carbon copy of typed lyric sheet; [1] p. (Box-folder 2/1)
      - All dark people see: [Sketches for Babes in Arms]
      - Babes in arms see: [Sketches for Babes in Arms]
      - I wish I were in love again, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [4] p. (Box-folder 2/2)
      - Imagine, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [4] p. (Box-folder 2/3)
      - Imagine ballet, or, [Peter's journey], Holograph condensed score in pencil; 22 p. (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Johnny one note, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; 6 p. (Box-folder 2/5)
      - The lady is a tramp, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [5] p. (Box-folder 2/6)
      - [My funny] valentine, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [4] p. (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Peter's journey see: Imagine ballet
      - Where or when, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [4] p. (Box-folder 2/8)
      - You are so fair, Holograph piano-vocal score in pencil; [4] p.; Laid in: typed lyric sheet with pencil annotation; [1] p. (Box-folder 2/9)